<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Brittaines hallelujah or A sermon of thanksgiving for the happy pacification in Brittaine preached in the English church at Hamburch before his excellency the right honorable Sir Thomas Rovve Lord Ambassador Extraordinary for his Mayesty of Greate Brittaine in Germany, &amp;c. And to the vvorshipfull &amp; famous Society of Merchant Adventurers &amp; some cavelliers of Scotland By Ma. Harris Batchelour in Divinity, fellovv of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge &amp; chaplaine to his excellency.</title>
            <author>Harris, Malachi, 1606 or 7-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855028</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855028</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20498</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02675)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20498)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 578:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Brittaines hallelujah or A sermon of thanksgiving for the happy pacification in Brittaine preached in the English church at Hamburch before his excellency the right honorable Sir Thomas Rovve Lord Ambassador Extraordinary for his Mayesty of Greate Brittaine in Germany, &amp;c. And to the vvorshipfull &amp; famous Society of Merchant Adventurers &amp; some cavelliers of Scotland By Ma. Harris Batchelour in Divinity, fellovv of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge &amp; chaplaine to his excellency.</title>
                  <author>Harris, Malachi, 1606 or 7-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Hamburg? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M. DC. XXXIX. [1639]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Suggested place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20498:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20498:1"/>
            <p>BRITTAINES HALLELUJAH OR A SERMON OF THANKSGIVING For the happy Pacification in BRITTAINE Preached in the English Church at Hamburch before HIS EXCELLENCY THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR THOMAS ROVVE LORD AMBASSA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOR EXTRA ORDINARY FOR HIS MAYE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY OF GREATE BRITTAINE IN GERMANY, &amp;c. And to The VVorshipfull &amp; famous Society of MERCHANT ADVENTURERS &amp; ſome Cavelliers of SCOTLAND</p>
            <p>By MA. HARRIS Batchelour in Divinity, Fellovv of EMMANUEL Colledge in CAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRIDGE &amp; Chaplaine to his EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLENCY.</p>
            <p>ANNO M.DC.XXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20498:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable SIR THOMAS ROVVE Knight, Gentleman, of the Privy Chamber, Chancelor &amp; Treaſurer of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, His Majeſty of Greate Brittaines Ambaſſador Extraordinary to the King of Denmarke and other Princes &amp; States in Germany &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Eaner &amp; Baſer Mettalls may paſſe Curant, vvhen once they have paſſed the Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Mint. There is noe other Lyfe in my Hopes of this Poore Things Acceptance abroade, but this that it beares Your Lordships Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe vpon it. T'vvas your Lordship, that firſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded de It to the Eare, and novv to the Eye. If to Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther It did, or shall give little Content; It knovves vvhere to take Sanctuary. Only in this Jam rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied, that it may publish to the VVorld your constant Zeale &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to your Country: for vvhoſe ſake you conſecrated a day of Publique Thancksgiving here.</p>
            <p>To mention your Lordships Name any further: vvere to tell the vvorld There is a Sunne, vvhoſe
<pb facs="tcp:20498:2"/>Fellovv-Traveller you have bin. Both Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spheares knovv you vvell, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bleſſe you much. I knovv your Lordship too vviſe and too Good to he flattered. And yet He that shall render you but halfe of your dues must needes incurre that Cenſure, in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them (if there be any) that knovv you not. Hovv Greate &amp; Good a Stateſman you have all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvays approved your ſelfe in thoſe your many &amp; High employments abroade: vvhat Princes Court, or remoteſt Country doth not amply teſtifie? I neede not tell your ovvne Country, vvhat a True Patriot, nor your ovvne Univerſity,<note place="margin">Oxon.</note> vvhat a Noble Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, nor your Holy Mother the Church vvhat a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Sonne you have ever bin.</p>
            <p>There is an Epitaph vpon the tombe of of a Demi-Founder of a Colledge much commended for its Fullnes &amp; Modeſty. <hi>Fui Cajus,<note place="margin">Gonvell. &amp; Caj. Coll. in Camb.</note> I vvas Cajus.</hi> Identicall Propoſitions, vvhere the Subject is high ſpeake high, vvitneſſe thoſe of the Divine Ma<hi rend="sup">ty</hi>. Let me only alter the Perſon, &amp; the Tenſe (I pray God it may long &amp; long be Preſent) and his Epitaph is your Elogie, as little &amp; as much as can be ſayd, <hi>You are Sir Thomas Rovve.</hi> One vvho lives much De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired (as any that carrys ſuch a Head and ſuch a Heart) and therefore must neceſſarily dye much Lamented. And ſo vvill your other ſelfe your Noble
<pb facs="tcp:20498:3"/>Conſort. VVho as she is in her Houſe the exact An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titype of Solomons Vertuous VVoeman Prov. 31. v. 10. <hi>&amp; deinceps:</hi> ſo doe her vvorkes prayſe her in the Gates, in Publique, as vvell Eleemoſynall as Thera peuticall, I for beare to mention thoſe many Church ornaments her Fingers hath vvrought, Her other Maſculine &amp; Heroicall vertues rayſe Her above Her ſexe. But I knovv I ſtrike too long vpon this ſtringe to you Both, vvhoſe ſtudy is, <hi>bene potiùs facere quàm audire</hi> rather to <hi>Doe vvell, then to Heare vvell.</hi> I have done, vvhen I have only, ſupplicated the Divine Majeſty for your Lordships Health. (for I knovv none that conque'rs ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultys of Buſines vvho vvreſtles vvith ſuch infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitys &amp; paines of Body) and for the continuance of a proſperous ſucceſſe in your greate &amp; vveighty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and for Both your Aeternall Happines, vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I knovv you tend as your Motto ſpeakes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prays</hi> TRAMITE RECTA. <hi>Your Lordships</hi> Most humble Devoted. <hi>Chaplaine</hi> MA. HARRIS</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20498:3"/>
            <head>BRITTAINS HALLELUIAH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalme CXXVI. v. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord hath done greate things for vs, vvhereof vve are glad <hi>or</hi> novv reioyce.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Text ſo melodiously tuned to this bleſſed occaſion, that, I knovv not vvhether, the Compoſer, vvere more Patheticall in that their Hallelujah, or, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall of this of ours. If ever, <hi>They among the Heathen</hi> could ſay. <hi>The Lord hath done greate things for them</hi> of vvhom can they ſay it, if not of vs? and vvhen if not novv? If ever any Church can ſing <hi>The Lord hath done greate things for vs</hi> vvhat Church can doe it rather then ours? and at vvhat Time rather then this? vvhen the De liverance is ſo exceeding greate, the Circumſtances ſo vvonderfully vvonderfull: that at the firſt entertainement of the nevves vve vvere in the Churche's caſe in the firſt verſe of this Pſalme <hi>like them that drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,</hi> as fearing, leaſt vve rather imaginarily dream't it sleeping, then credibly heard it vvaking.</p>
            <p>But novv it is avouched vvith ſuch vndeneyable proofes that vve muſt be ſayd to <hi>dreame</hi> indeede if yet vve doubt of it: let
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20498:4"/>vs having firſt ſett our hearts in tune to a thankfull Comemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then fill our mouth's vvith ioy full Acclamations &amp; ſingings. That ſo, both Cordially &amp; vocally, vve may ioyne in conſort vvith Sion here. <hi>The Lord hath done, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Greate things?</hi> vvhat greate things vvere thoſe that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo greate thanks? Yea, that's the <hi>Point</hi> vpon vvhich the vvhole Pſalme runns deſcant, the very <hi>Gam ut</hi> of the Pſal. according to vvhich, vve are to take our notes anon, in our Counter-Tenor.</p>
            <p>To ſet the Pſalme then for Them firſt, then for our ſelvs: let this be the taske of this time.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>greate things</hi> done them here, vvere a greate Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, a Deliverance from Captivity, from Captivity in Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. This vvas that, vvhich ſet them here on ſinging and gave both Time, and Tune to this Pſalme.</p>
            <p>Which (as moſt of the reſt doe) conſiſts of tvvo Parts.</p>
            <p>Of an <hi>Hallelujah</hi> prayſes.</p>
            <p>Of an <hi>Hoſanna</hi> a prayer: ſo a greate Prelate hath divided it before me.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">B. Andr.</note> An <hi>Hallelujah</hi> &amp;c. prayſes for favours allready obtained.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Hoſanna</hi> a prayer, either for the continuing of the ſame favour ſtill, or, for the like, vpon the like occaſion, as vve shall touch vpon anou.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt, the <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> that takes vp the 3. firſt verſes. And as thankſgiving is allvvays founded vpon ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour received, ſo, according to the height of the one, the other is ſtill elevated. High prayſes for high favours. This is good in the common lavv of gratitude. What then vvas the favour done the Church here? that's the Queſtion, and hath bin allready anſvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red-A Deliverance from Babylonish Captivity.</p>
            <p>Novv into this (as all other favours) tvvo Inquirys, vvill be made. 1. <hi>vvhat vvas it?</hi> for the <hi>matter &amp; nature</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Hovv vvas it?</hi> for the <hi>manner</hi> &amp; order of doing it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the firſt, the <hi>matter and nature</hi> of a deliverance, that's vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20498:4"/>valued &amp; eſtimated by the Evill or Danger eſcaped: and ſo this of theirs vvill admitt of 2. degrees.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it vvas a Deliverance from <hi>Captivity</hi> one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of Evills. Secondly, it vvas from <hi>Babylonish Captivity,</hi> the very greateſt of all other Captivitys.</p>
            <p>Here is juſtly then an Hallelujah due to the Deliverance for the <hi>matter</hi> &amp; nature of it, that it vvas a Returne from captivity, that it vvas from ſuch a Captivity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And 2ly an Hallelujah againe vvill be noe leſſe due for the <hi>Manner</hi> of the Deliverance, The next Inquiry. <hi>Hovv vvas it done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It vvas done ſo <hi>vnexpectedly,</hi> that they vvere <hi>like them that dreame.</hi> As dreames vve knovv come vpon men vnlook'd for, vnthought of.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly It vvas done ſo <hi>vvithout any labour</hi> or <hi>ſeeking of theirs,</hi> that they vvere <hi>like them that dreamed</hi> againe faſt a sleepe perhaps vvhileſt it vvas doing. Or rather like them that <hi>dreamed not,</hi> for they never once dreamed of it, it vvas done ſo ſuddainly.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly It vvas done ſo <hi>graciously</hi> that at the firſt hearing of the good nevvs, they vvere ſo amazed vvith Joy, that they knevv not, vvhether they vvere in a. <hi>Dreame</hi> or noe, vvhether they might truſt their ſenſes, vvhen they both heard, and ſavv it.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. It vvas done ſo <hi>miraculously,</hi> that it manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, to be the <hi>Lords doing,</hi> and ſo <hi>became marveilous</hi> not only <hi>in their eyes</hi> but <hi>in the eyes</hi> of the very Heathen, <hi>They among the Heathen could ſay. The Lord hath done &amp;c. v. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And shall the Heathen ſay it, and shall not Sion ſing it? yes I vvarrant you, vvith their heart-ſtrings tuned to the higheſt pitch, vvith their voices elevated to the higheſt note. <hi>The Lord hath done &amp;c. v. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20498:5"/>
            <p> Thus farre their Hallelujah, or prayſes, the firſt part of the Pſalme.</p>
            <p>The Second vvas their Hoſanna or prayer. v. 4. <hi>Turne againe our Captivity.</hi> That is Either Continue to turne it, confirme, and ratifie vvhat thou haſt allready done Or, turne is hereafter, if not <hi>praeveniendo</hi> that the like Calamity befalls vs noe more: yet at the leaſt <hi>Subveniendo,</hi> that vve may have a like taſt of ſuch goodnes in ſuch an happy enlargement as this vvas.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Turne, vs like the ſtreames in the ſouth</hi> And this shall be as vvellcome to vs as the vvater ſtreames to thoſe deſarts (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of Arabia) in the dry Southerne Clymates as Vatablus vvill have it. Or turne vs in a facile melting vvay (as novv they did'ſt by Cyrus) even as thoſe vvaterbrooks in the South are cauſed by the melting of the ſnovv upon the neighbour mountaines, as that greate Bishop of ours. Then shall it fare vvith us, as it doth vvith Husband men in a greate dearth; hovvſoever <hi>they may ſovve in teares</hi> (vvhether for the deare price of the ſeede corne, or the ſmall hopes of a Crop) yet a plentifull harveſt makes them a good amends for all: ſo though vve may goe into Captivity vvith teares, by vveeping croſſe: yet shall our Returne be vvith greare Joy like the joy in a greare Harveſt after a greate Dearth.</p>
            <p>And thus you have the Pſalme analyſed and para phraſed.</p>
            <p>But vve have made choice only of one verſe, the third. Which, as for its Situation in the middle of the Pſalme, it may be called <hi>Cor Pſalmi,</hi> the Heart of the Pſalme: ſo for its Nature (like the Heart in the Body) it is the ſeate of all thoſe vitall Spirits and ſtrong Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that are diffuſed in the vvhole body of the Pſalme. You heare hovv liuely and pathetically it renders it ſelfe</p>
            <p>The Lord hath done &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion.</note> And this Verſicle vvill be ſett in tvvo parts.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. Magnalia Dei</hi> greate things the Lord hath done for his Church.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20498:5"/> 2. <hi>Magnificat Eccleſiae,</hi> the Church her <hi>Magnificat</hi> or thankfull acknovvledgment of theſe greate things thus done by the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Magna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia Dei.</note> In the former three things are in ſight
<list>
                  <item>1. The Benefit Greate things</item>
                  <item>2. The Benefactor the Greate God Jehovah.</item>
                  <item>3. The Beneficed (ſo to ſpeake) the Church.</item>
               </list> We beginne vvith the Benefit, becauſe that is firſt in Nature,<note place="margin">1. The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</note> being the <hi>fundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> relationis</hi> bevvene the Benefactor, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver of the Benefit.</p>
            <p>The Benefit is expreſſed by Greate things, greate things interpreted a greate Deliverance v. 1. and every Deliverance allvvays ſo much the greater by hovv much the greater the Evill is from vvhich vve are delivered, and by hovv much the greater providence vvas ſeene in the manner of the deliverance. So that this Deliverance of Sion here layes claime to its greatenes, vpon a double title, firſt in regard of the Subſtance of it, ſecondly, in reſpect of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. For its Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> Firſt it is greate for the Subſtance, and this againe in a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble degree. Firſt as it vvas a Returne from captivity that is greate. Secondly, as it vvas a Returne from Babylonish Captivity, this is yet greater.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from Cape.</note> Firſt it vvas a Returne from Captivity. Novv to our Rule. The meaſure of the Mercy muſt be the miſery eſcaped. Is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity a greate miſery? Doth any man doubt it? Let him aske Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. in Lament. 4.9. <hi>They that fell by the ſvvord vvere in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caſe then they that vvent into Captivity.</hi> And yet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid in that his greate ſtreight, choſe rather the Peſtilence, then the ſvvord. Muſt not that then be a greate evill, that is greater then that, vvich is greater then the Peſtilence? But vvhy doe I name but one place in the Lamentations? The vvhole booke is but one intire proofe of the miſerys of Captivity.</p>
            <p>Captivity a greate Evill? Doth any man queſtion it? Let him aske him ſelfe: Is it nat a greate evill to be plundered &amp; ſpoiled
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20498:6"/>of all one's goods at once? And yet a man may be bereaved of his vvhole eſtate, and yet have that, vvhich he may have that hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in goods, his Liberty. Well then is Reſtraint a greate evill? The bird in the cage vvill tell you it is. And yet a man may be in hold vpon very good termes, and among good freinds. Is it a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te evill then to be taken Priſoner by an Enemy? a cruel feirce ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, vvhoſe mercys are cruelty?</p>
            <p>Say! Are bitter taunts? inſulting reproches? cruell oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? remote Banishment? the extreamity of all manner of hatd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship? are theſe greate, evills? vvhat then shall vve make of Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that hath ſo many legions of greate evills vvithin it? But vvhat ſpeake I of Banishment? Reſtraint? Poverty? theſe are but the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Body, and ſo are but the bodys and carkaſſes of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. There are afflictions of the Soule and they are the Soules of afflictions. And this vvas their caſe. Not only in Captivity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. from Babylon: Capt.</note> But 2ly in <hi>Babylonish Captivity,</hi> that is a degree higher of their miſery. They vvere Captives in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Babylon,</hi> vvhere true Religion is ſcoffed and gybe dat <hi>Come, and ſing vs one of the ſongs of Sion Pſalm. 137.4.</hi> This alone vvas enough to ſet open sluices to their teares as they <hi>ſate by the Rivers of Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Babylon,</hi> vvhere the groſſeſt Idolatry is vrged vvith all madnes of violence. Either fall dovvne and vvorship this Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, or vvhat? noe more a doe but <hi>into the fiery furnace</hi> vvith them Dan. 3. Was it not enough for them to leade their Bodys captive, but vvould they leade avvay their ſoules alſo? Can there be greater evills (on this ſide Hell) then theſe? And may not a faire Deliverance out of all theſe be counted <hi>greate things?</hi> That is the Firſt, greate for the <hi>Subſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for its Circumſt.</note> And 2ly as greate for the <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> and manner of bringing it about. Had they bin able to have made any Head, or Reſiſtance, themſelvs: the matter had not bin ſo greate. A
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20498:6"/>violent Revolt from vnder an Enemy is not ſo greately ſtrange in the vvorld. But vvhat could a company of poore, forlorne, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed Captives doe a gainſt ſo mighty a Potentate? Or had they had ſome good able Freinds abroad, to ſend them in ſuccours for their reſcue it had bin ſomething. Forraine ſupplies have done greate matters in this kinde. But alas, they vvere the object of contempt &amp; Deriſion to the vvhole vvorld. Or had they els, any good Freinds at Court, vvho being ſett vpon the vantage ground of greate favour, might have ventured to ſollicite the king in their b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>halfe: there had bin ſome shadovv of hope. But alas! vvhat freindes vvere ſuch contemptible vvretches like to make? Or vvhat Courtier durſt vouchſafe an eare to ſuch a motion, vvhich ſeemed to claſsh againſt all lavves and rules of State-policy? Or laſtly had the king himſelfe bin a vvorshiper of the true God: Religion might have ſvvayed him tovvards a propitions Inclination. But as for him, He vvas an abſolute Idolater, and ſo not only a ſtranger but an enemy to their Religion. Which vvay shall this deſighne be compaſſe'd? vvho shall roule avvay theſe ſo many, and ſo greate ſtones thus vvedged one in another? Noe Povver in themſelves, noe hopes from any Freind at home or abroad, noe thinking of dealing vvith the king himſelfe: yet God vndertakes it, and it shall not faile of taking effect. Cyrus himſelf shall be moved to doe it, and that voluntarily and ſpontaneously, that peremptorily &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely maugre all ſuggeſtions &amp; counſells to the contrary, that magnificently and munificently, He shall enable them vvith all the force of Diplomaticall letters and decrees, furnish them vvith all accommodations vvhatſoever. Verily ſuch mighty things (Pſ. 118. 16.) could not have bin brought to paſſe but by <hi>the right Hand of the Lord, vvhich hath the preeminence.</hi> Doubtles it vvas the <hi>Lords doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor.</note> And this mindes me of the ſecond Particular.</p>
            <p>The Benefactor, the Lord. The Lord hath done &amp;c. His name vvas vvritten vpon the Fact in ſuch capital lettets, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20498:7"/>the blinde Heathen could ſee and reade it <hi>The Lord hath done greate things for them</hi> ſayd they And it is not perhaps vnvvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your obſervation, that in this their Doxologicall acknovvle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dgment, they hit vpon the <hi>Tetragrammaton, Jehovah,</hi> for ſo the Hebrevv hath it in that their verſe. v. 2. They attributed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this to Fortune or chance, or any falſe God, or to any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe but expreſsly pronounce it done by the <hi>Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> It is the <hi>finger of the Lord,</hi> cryed out the Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Aegyptians, and among them the moſt Divelish Magicians. Yea and <hi>Brachiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei</hi> it vvas, <hi>the out ſtretched arme of the Lord,</hi> that all the nations felt, vvhen Iſrael is to paſſe into Canaan. And novv I have mentioned Iſraels paſſage into Canaan, let that one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſerve for a Demonſtration in this matter.</p>
            <p>For their removing out of Aegypt, vvho muſt be their Spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſman, but ſtammering Moſes, but obnoxious Moſes? (for it vvere ſtrange if the Eminency of the man a famous Courtier, and his ſuddaine flight out of the Land, should not recall that Fact into the mindes of ſome of his Cooetaneans.) yet this man muſt be the man. I paſſe over the <hi>Categories</hi> of thoſe vvonders done in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt. Looke vve upon the <hi>Tranſcendency of Gods povver and providence,</hi> novv they are on their vvay. Doe they vvant a Guide for their vvay? God him ſelfe goeth before them in fire. Doe they vvant a Shelter? His cloude is ſpread over them for a covering Doe they vvant vvay? the Sea it ſelfe shall make it, and at once be a ſtreete and a vvall vnto them. Doe they vvant bread? Heaven it ſelfe shall raine dovvne Angells foode. Doe they vvant meate to their bread? The very vvind shall become their Cater, and bring them vvhole drifts of Quailes into their tents. Doe they vvant drinke to both? The Rock it ſelfe shall be their Sellar and yeild it them in abundance. Doe they vvant Change of Apparrell? Their cloaths shall not vveare olde on their backs. Doe they vvant counſell and adviſe? God Himſelfe vvill be their oracle from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveene
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20498:7"/>the Cherubims. Doe they vvant a Lavv? Himſelfe vvil ſitt vpon the <hi>Bench,</hi> on mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and give them their <hi>charge</hi> in <hi>Perſon,</hi> and vvrite it vpon tables vvith his ovvne <hi>fingers.</hi> Are they reſiſted by Enemys? God himſelfe diſchargeth volleys of haile ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vpon their heads, and braines them to their hands. Are they to ſitt before Jerico? The Tovvnevvalls of themſelvs shall fall dovvne flatt before them. Is Joshuah to pitch a Battaile? The Sun muſt ſtand ſtill, to ſee him have the Victory. O the greate and mighty things the Lord did for Iſrael? I cannot have vvhile ſo much as to vnclaſpe any more volumnes, vvherein are recorded Gods ſtrange doings for his Church in all ages. It ſuſticeth, that a Devoute Bishop, hath folded you dovvne ſome fevv leaves,<note place="margin">B. Hall.</note> in that booke vvhich is moſt knovvne, I hope to the moſt. God doth uſe to appeare ſo for his Church, that he ſticks not, to put it among his <hi>Titles Royall</hi> (nay makes it his <hi>Cognomen</hi> ſayth Petrarch) <hi>the God of Abraham</hi> and of his ſeede. vvhich in the Apoſtles expoſition, is the vvhole <hi>houſehold of the faithfull,</hi> the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. The Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</note> And this calls me to the <hi>third</hi> and laſt Particular the <hi>Receiver</hi> of <hi>the Benefit,</hi> the <hi>delivered.</hi> The Church. <hi>For vs,</hi> ſayth the Text. <hi>The Lord hath done greate things for vs.</hi> And vvhat vvere vve might Sion ſay (vvho vvere glad to lick the duſt of the feete of our Enemys) that the Lord of Heaven &amp; Earth should looke ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously vpon vs? The meanenes of the Receiver argueth the magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence of the Giver. <hi>Who am I that the Mother of my Lord</hi> should viſit me? It vvas a true, and religious complement of devout Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth. The beſt of men, are but the children of duſt, and grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children of nothing. And yet for the Lord to doe <hi>greate things</hi> for vs? this yet <hi>greatens</hi> thoſe <hi>greate things.</hi> Was it be cauſe vve vvere his Church? It vvas his ſuper-abounding grace, to ſelect vs out of others, as, it vvas our greater graceleſnes, above all others, ſo to provoke Him, as to force him, to throvve vs into Captivity. Or vvas it, becauſe our Humiliation, in that diſconſolate condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did move him to ſo greate compaſſion? Alas! there vvas choice of Nations, vvhom he might have taken in our roome, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20498:8"/>might have proved farre more faithfull then vve had bin, for the one halfe of thoſe favours, vve had enioyed.</p>
            <p>Or vvas it for his <hi>Covenants</hi> ſake vvith our Fore-fathers? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! vve had forfeited That long ſince, againe &amp; againe vve knovv not hovv often.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, vvhen vve remember our ſelvs, vve cannot but make this an Aggravation of Gods <hi>greate things,</hi> that he should doe them <hi>for vs, for vs,</hi> ſo very very vnvvorthy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 2. Generall Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. Eccl.</note> And ſo much be ſpoken to the firſt <hi>Generall Magnalia Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next is, <hi>Magnificat Eccleſiae.</hi> The Church her ſolemne thankſgiving &amp; reioycing for thoſe <hi>greate things</hi> the Lord had do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne for Her. We can but glaunce at it novv, leaſt vve prae occupate our buſines that is behind. This <hi>Magnificat</hi> likevviſe vvill beare 2. Parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. a Pious Commemoration &amp; Acknovvledgment.</item>
               <item>2. a Joy full Jubile or Exultation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the <hi>firſt</hi> the Churches <hi>Soule magnifies the Lord,</hi> by her thankfull Acknovvledgment of the <hi>Benefit.</hi> In the <hi>Second,</hi> the Churches <hi>Spirit reioyoeth in God her Sauiour,</hi> by her Panegyricall ſolemnization of the Benefit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> Firſt she <hi>gratefully acknovvledgeth is.</hi> Yea but this the Heathen did' too, <hi>vvhen they ſayd among themſelvs The Lord hath done &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> True! they acknovvledged it indeede. The thing vvas ſo clearely and evidentsly done before their eyes; that they could not but ſee it, and ſay it. But vvhether they did ſo greatefully acknovvledge it, that is a Queſtion, or rather noe Queſtion. Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bably, ſome of them ſavv it vvith the Eye of Envy, and vvhen they had ſayd it, bitt their lips for anger that it vvas done. Certainely, none of them could ſpeake of it vvith that Affection, the Church did. Whom alone it concerned as a Receiver, They but meere ſpectators the vvhiles.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20498:8"/> 2. Next, she <hi>ſölemnly reioyceth.</hi> And this Joy you have. 1. in the <hi>fountaine</hi> 2. in the <hi>Streames.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>In the fountaine.</hi> It vvas a reioycing in the <hi>Heart.</hi> v. 4. So much the vvord <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeemes to import.</item>
               <item>2. This Joy <hi>ſtreames</hi> forth, and derives itſelfe into theſe 3. channells.
<list>
                     <item>1. Into the <hi>Countenance</hi> that is filled vvith <hi>laughter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Into the <hi>Tongue,</hi> that runns over vvith <hi>prayſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Into the <hi>Hand</hi> v. 2. For beſides, that it vvas their vſuall cuſtome, vpon ſuch occaſions, to ſend gifts to their neighbours, and largeſſes to to the poore; beſides this (vvhich carrys ſome faire probability, they did it novv) the very <hi>penning</hi> of this pſalme, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies their <hi>hands</hi> vvere not id idle: vvhen they tooke order for ſuch a durable memoriall to be transmitted to Poſterity. So then; It vvas a <hi>Cordiall, hearty</hi> joy, It vvas a <hi>laughing viſible</hi> joy it vvas a <hi>manuall, legible, durable</hi> joy, that the poeple vnborne might for many ages pervſe it.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And thrice happy vve, <hi>vvho are a poeple</hi> novv <hi>in ſuch caſe,</hi> that vve may juſtly take vp the ſame vvords, chaunt forth the ſame <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> vpon an occaſion not much leſſe greate. <hi>The Lord hath done greate things for vs,</hi> too, <hi>vvhereof vve reioyce</hi> alſo:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Text to vs.</note> This vvas our ſecond promiſe in the beginning: To ſett this pſalme to our ſelvs: vvhich novv vve come to performe as the duty of the day bindes vs ſtrongly.</p>
            <p>But then, vve muſt needes ſett it in a farre higher, <hi>cliffe.</hi> Our notes if you pleaſe, shall ſtand ſome in <hi>ſpace,</hi> ſome in <hi>Rule:</hi> My meanning is vve vvill looke a little <hi>backvvard</hi> to former times (but this shall be diſpatched in a <hi>Sembreife</hi> or tvvo) and then <hi>cloſe</hi> vvith the <hi>Diapaſon</hi> of this Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Greate things</hi> (may our Iſrael ſay) <hi>the Lord hath done for vs. Greate things</hi> and a <hi>greate many greate things.</hi> To ſingle out only 3. remarkeables.</p>
            <p>It is very vvell vvorthy your conſideration, hovv that (ſince the Reformation of our Church.) Our 3. laſt Gracious Princes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20498:9"/>(vnder vvhoſe bleſſed goverments She hath ſeeue ſuch golden days) hath had each ones ſeverall <hi>Reighne</hi> erovvned vvith ſome notable ſingular Deliverance: and every Deliverance a degree hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher then its precedent.</p>
            <p>You knovv vvhat I vvould. That of 88 That of Novemb. 5. This late happy Pacification.</p>
            <p>That learned &amp; holy Lord Bishop, af Chicheſter Bp. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton, hath published a Booke entituled A Thankfull Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Church of England. You are vvell acquainted vvith it Jam ſure. And in the <hi>Frontiſpice</hi> of that Booke (as I remember) he hath ſett the Portraitures, of <hi>Q. ELIZABETH</hi> (of renovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned memory,) vvith a <hi>Flagg</hi> in her hand, in vvhich is deſcribed, the, <hi>Spanish-Armado</hi> in 88. as alſo, of <hi>King JAMES</hi> (of ever fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous &amp; bleſſed memory) vvith his <hi>Flagg,</hi> and in it the <hi>Parlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, houſe, the vault &amp;c. Nov. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I verily beleiue, if the Reverend Father had lived to ſee this day: He vvould have a founde a roome for <hi>king CHARLES</hi> too (our moſt Gracious ſoveraigne) vvith his <hi>Flagg</hi> in His hand like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe. Wherein should have bin expreſſed thoſe late vnhappy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations in Brittaine, and this moſt happy Reconciliation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <p>It vvill be too greate an Expence of Time to diſplay the firſt of theſe <hi>Banners.</hi> You cannot be ignorant of it. It vvere only to be vvished, It had ſomevvhat a fresher varnish. It begins to grovv ſo old, that it is too much vvorne out of our memorys. But it muſt be acknovvledged, to the vvorlds end, That, it vvas one of Gods <hi>greate things</hi> done for our Island. When ſuch a <hi>Navy</hi> named the <hi>Armado,</hi> Sirnamed <hi>Invincible:</hi> shall ſo ſuddainely, ſo eaſily be diſſipated, be defeated.</p>
            <p>I have much a doe to let it paſſe vvishout an Hallelujah. Me thinks, It runns vpon <hi>Eights</hi> of it ſelfe, on purpoſe for a <hi>Song.</hi> Lord vvhat <hi>greate things didſt thon then doe</hi> for that thy bleſſed Servant, and Her Realme! vvhen Thou ſeemed'ſt to ſuffer the <hi>ſea and Windes to obey Her,</hi> as if they had taken Pay vnder her.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20498:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> But there is a nevver, fresher Flagg, (King JAMES His) vvhich deſireth rather to belooked vpon, as it tells vs of a <hi>later</hi> &amp; <hi>greater</hi> Deliverance. That of Novemb. 5.</p>
            <p>The former vvas from an Invaſion of a forraine Enemy, and (if you vvill,) of a cruell proude one, therefore noe leſſe could be expected from Them. I vvould allmoſt all Chriſtendome, and the Indys to boote, did not ſvveate and bleede—Under Their Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. But This (vve are novv to ſpeake of) vvas from a Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Conſpirancy. All the Actors our ovvne Coungion is Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, our Fellovv Subjects, till Treaſon &amp; Rome (vvhoſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion) had diſſolved that <hi>vinculum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Conſpiracy it vvas, vvhich noe Age can parallell, and vvhich (but for its Annuall Commemoration) vvould be thought by Poſterity, to be all to geather incredible.</p>
            <p>A Conſpiracy, vvherein Malice vvas armed vvith Fortitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, Fortitude animated vvith Policy, Policy masked vvith Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Secrecy inveſted vvith Religion. They counterfeited, the <hi>Broade Seale</hi> of Heaven, and vvould have it rati-fied vvith a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: Lord! vvhat Preparations vvere there vvhat a Brevving of death (it is a BP<hi rend="sup">s</hi> expreſſion) vvas tunned vp in thoſe barrells. Povvder, Billets, Barrs, and I knovv not vvhat ſtore of Hellish proviſion, as if they had meaned to have made an Earth-quake throughout the vvhole, Island. What ayled ye, O ye Sonns of the Cole! What mean't ye, O ye Fire-brands, and Granados of Hell (Pardon me, I cannot be vncharitable vnles Repentance came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) vvhat meant ye I ſay? Was it your purpoſe to Trans-late, the king, his nobles and the vvhole ſtate repreſentative, to transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, them all into Heaven in an Inſtant, by an Extemporary Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Was it your meaning preſumptuously to prevent a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and to preferre Companions to Elias in fiery Charriots?</p>
            <p>A Conſpiracy, vvherein, all the Crueltys that have bin heard of, or can be Imagined vvere mett to geather, as our late Greate <hi>&amp; Good L. Bishop of Wincheſter</hi> vvell obſerved. The Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of <hi>Pharoh &amp; Herod,</hi> murdering, the harmeles, Innocent,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20498:10"/>harmeles Infants and yet they ſpared the mothers. The Cruelty of <hi>Eſau</hi> killing the mothers vvith the Children; The cruelty of <hi>Nebuzaradan</hi> not ſparing the King, and his Nobles, The Cruelty of <hi>Haman</hi> not ſparing <hi>Eſther</hi> &amp; her Ladys. The Cruelty of <hi>Edom,</hi> not ſparing the Sanctuary and its vvalls. <hi>Dovvne vvith them, Dovvne vvith them</hi> to the very ground: Or rather <hi>vp vvith them vp vvith them</hi> into the higheſt Region of the Aire. The Cruelty of the <hi>Divel Himſelfe,</hi> hurling dovvne the foure corners of the Houſe Shall I ſay? or of the vvhole Citty? vpon the moſt and beſt of the ſonns of the Church &amp; State As if <hi>Lucifer Himſelfe,</hi> had not bin (before this time) either old &amp; vvitty enough to plott, or miſcheivous enough to attempt ſuch a damnable deſolation, as this vvould have proved. And vvas not the Deliverance from this a <hi>greate thing?</hi> that ſo diſmall a Calamity should be praevented by the vnridling of an <hi>aenigmaticall letter</hi> directed to a freind? A <hi>Letter in</hi> deede vvich in the event did <hi>ſalutem plurimam dicere</hi> brought moſt happy ſalutations to the vvhole Church and ſtate: But vve muſt thanke (next Allmighty God) King <hi>JAMES.</hi> Of vvhom it might be better ſaid, then once it vvas of a greate Orator <hi>Miſerum eſſet eum tacuiſſe</hi> It had bin a miſerable thing if He had held his peace. Had there not bin <hi>Divinatio in labijs Regis, a divine ſentence in the lips of the king</hi> Prov. 16.10. (As if King Salomon had purpoſely vvrit that ſaying to be verified in his <hi>Succeſſor in Wiſdome</hi> vpon this occaſion.) Had there not bin I ſay a Divination in the kings <hi>Lips</hi> (I may ſpeake it after that Reverend Prelate) vve had bin all in the <hi>Javves</hi> of death, <hi>vvere not theſe greate things vvhich the Lord hath done for vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this you vvill ſay is more pro per to a 5th of Novemb. Well then vve turne over the Calendar, to the <hi>Moneth of June</hi> this 1639. and looke vpon <hi>King CHARLES his Flagg,</hi> the juſt Trophy of this day.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20498:10"/>
            <p> But here I am vlterly at a loſſe, and knovv not vvhich vvay to turne my ſelfe. Yet you may &amp; muſt pardon me <hi>loquuntur leves</hi> as true of <hi>Joyes</hi> as of <hi>Greifes.</hi> Light Joyes may be Rhetoricall, vvhileſt ſuch as theſe knovv noe ether Figure then an Eckſtaticall Apoſiopeſis.</p>
            <p>It deſervedly takes place of both the former The <hi>firſt</hi> vvas from a <hi>forraine Invaſion.</hi> The <hi>Second</hi> takes place of it as It vvas from a <hi>domeſtick Conſpiracy.</hi> This <hi>Third</hi> of them both, both as it vvas from an <hi>Inſurrection,</hi> and ſo of an higher nature then a <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> and as it vvas made by men of the ſame <hi>Church</hi> of the ſame <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſo outſtrips the <hi>ſecond</hi> That being done by men, though <hi>Brittaines</hi> by <hi>Nation</hi> yet <hi>Romans</hi> by <hi>Relegion,</hi> vvith vvhom any thing is lavvfull, Treaſons, Rebellions, vvhat not, in <hi>or dine ad Deum</hi> they ſay, <hi>ad Diabolum</hi> they should ſay.</p>
            <p>Here I might vvell take leave to make a Reviſall of vvhat hath bin ſpoken concerning <hi>Sions</hi> Deliverance: and compare this of ours vvith that of Theirs both for <hi>Matter &amp; Manner,</hi> that ſo the Praeeminency of ours may more manifeſtly appeare. We vvill be very breife.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Matter. You vvill ſay perhaps, there vvas noe feare of a <hi>Babylonish Captivity.</hi> Well vve let that paſſe novv But there vvas a greate feare of a moſt bloudy <hi>vvarre,</hi> vvas there not? And doe you knovv vvhat <hi>vvarre</hi> is. Can you tell me vvhat horrid confuſions there are in one pitched feild? vvhat roaring &amp; thundering of Canons? vvhat clashing of armor? What ſvveating &amp; ſvvimming in bloud? vvhat hideous outerys? My leg is of, my arme is of, my gutts be out, halfe dead, halfe aliue, vvorſe then either becauſe neither, as one deſcribes it pathetically. Can you tell me the direfull Iſſues of a victory? vvhat plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, &amp; burnings? vvhat killing and encouraging to kill? vvhat amazed flights? vvhat fearefull ſcreichings? Noe regard of Age, or Place or Sexe, The Grayheaded vvallovving.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20498:11"/>in their goare, vnder the hand of a fell-ruffian-ſouldier. The ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Infants either dashed a gainſt the ſtones, or ſpravvling vpon the points of ſpeares. The ſcreaming Mother the vvhiles, bruitish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ravishedere she may have leave to be slayne. Doe but looke out of your ovvne doores, a little higher into theſe Countrys. Hovv are thoſe gardens of Eden become deſolate vvilderneſſes! Hovv many miles may you travell ere you finde a Dorpe! Hovv many Dorpes may you paſſe thorough ere you meete vvith a man? Meete vvith a man ſayd I? Nay rather one vvhom you vvill ſtartle at, as at a Ghoſt, and runne avvay from, as from a <hi>Lycan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropus.</hi> Have you not heardl (I am ſure you have and that often and that by very good hands) vvhat monſtrous Metamorphoſeis <hi>Famine</hi> hath vvrought among them? vvhen the Hoſt shall lodge his Gueſts in his Mavv; vvhen freind shall bury freind in his belly; vvhen the mother shall entombe her child in her vvombe; vvhen the Living shall prey vpon the Carkaſſes of the dead. Nay vvhen (heare o Hell and be moved vvith pitty!) vvhen the dead shall be raked out of their graues, to beburied a <hi>ſecond</hi> time, in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack and a <hi>third</hi> time in the Draught. O the calamitys of vvarre vvhilſt the very relating of them can ſcarce ſecure you from teares! And is a Deliverance from a <hi>vvarre</hi> then, thinke you noe <hi>greate thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We doe not ſay (as many have) that it might have proved in the end a <hi>Captivity</hi> little better then <hi>Babylonish</hi> (vvhiles either a vvhole Church should be vvith out Goverment, or almoſt every private ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Church should become a Governour) yet againe vvhiles a Paire of Turtle-doves (it is but ſeldovvne I confeſſe) shall in an angry cholerick manner make feircely one at another vvho knovves but ſome Eagle, or Faulcon may be pearched not farre of, delighting to ſee ſuch a ſpectacle, and feeding her ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith hopes of preying vpon both?</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe this to be a groundles Suſpicion: yet a <hi>Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity</hi> it vvould queſtionles have bin, and for its kinde a very ſtrange one. Heare o Heavens and be amazed! Hearken o Earth and be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20498:11"/>aſtonished! <hi>Brittaine should have bin lead Captive by Brittaine Countryman</hi> by <hi>Countryman, Brother</hi> by <hi>Brother</hi> the <hi>Sonne</hi> by the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> by the <hi>Sonne. Coeter a loquantur lachrymae!</hi> Thus you ſee vve come not farre short of Sions Deliverance for the <hi>Matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor 2ly for the <hi>Manner</hi> I truſt. I knovv very vvell the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit is noe place for <hi>Currantos</hi> and <hi>Gizets</hi> noe place to tell nevvs in. It vvas my boldnes ere vvhile to phancy my <hi>Soveraighne</hi> vvith a <hi>Flag in his hand:</hi> let me novv be bold to adde his <hi>Deviſe</hi> &amp; <hi>motto,</hi> (that shall tell you in breife, the <hi>Manner</hi>) and it vvill be noe leſſe then vvhat vvas once attributed to another <hi>Caeſar</hi> in a different ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. <hi>Venit, vidit, vicit. He came,</hi> (He Himſelfe, <hi>Principem ſus Majeſtas defendit.</hi> It vvas his ovvne ſole act.) He <hi>came, looked vpon them,</hi> had conference vvith them, and inſtantly <hi>Overcame them,</hi> conquered them. Conquered Them? <hi>Their Hearts</hi> I meane. The happieſt Conqueſt that poſſibly could be. A ſtrange Conqueſt! vvherein both vvere conquerors, both conquered. The king con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered vvith the Loyall Submiſſion of the Subject. The Subject conquered, vvith the Royall Pardon of the king. Why <hi>Gracious Soveraighne!</hi> vvas it not enough for <hi>your Majeſty</hi> to ſucceede your <hi>Royall Father,</hi> in his <hi>Throane,</hi> in his Prinely endovvm ent? to vveare his <hi>Crovvne?</hi> to beare his <hi>Coate?</hi> but muſt you needes chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge his <hi>Motto</hi> too, <hi>Beati Pacifici?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto you ſee our Deliverance keepes good pace vvith that of Sions for the <hi>Manner.</hi> It being done in ſuch a <hi>thavving mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> vvay. Only in this it farre outruns that That vvas done <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniendo.</hi> They had ſmarted ſonndly vnder their myſeris many yeares, ere they vvere releaſed. Ours is done <hi>praeveniendo,</hi> vve vvere only Shevved the Danger, and fairely Delivered. Here is a Conduit vvould runne amaine, if vve could ſtay to turne the Coek.</p>
            <p>We have heard &amp; ſeene vvhat <hi>greate things the Lord hath done for vs. Greate</hi> for the <hi>Subſtance. Greate</hi> for the <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Greate</hi> as done by a <hi>Greate God,</hi> vvhoſe Praerogative Royall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20498:12"/>it is to turne the <hi>hearts of kings.</hi> Yet <hi>greater</hi> as done <hi>for vs</hi> ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthy a poeple. Another Topick, if vve had time to knock at that doore. And should not all theſe <hi>Magnalia Dei</hi> novv juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call for our <hi>Magnificat?</hi> Shall not our <hi>ſoules magnifie the Lord, and our Spirits reioyce in God our Saviour?</hi> I hope they <hi>shall</hi> and <hi>doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then as our <hi>Deliverance</hi> hath, ſo let our <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> and Reioycings likevviſe, runne parallell (at leaſt) vvith <hi>Sions</hi> here. Her <hi>Joy</hi> vvas a <hi>Cordiall hearty joy:</hi> ſo muſt ours procede from a true pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re heart. This Incenſe, vvould not be offered vp but in a golden Cenſer: Can Adulterys Can Murders, can Envyngs (vvhich our Saviour tells vs, loue to billet in the heart.) can theſe dead vvorkes prayſe the Lord? Her <hi>Joy</hi> vvas a <hi>viſible laughing Joy:</hi> ſo may ours be a <hi>merry</hi> one too. We may doe vvell to make merry, to <hi>drincke of the ſvvete, and eate of the fatt.</hi> Only let uſtake heede, vve ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke not vvorke for <hi>ſacrificings</hi> after our feaſtings, as Job vvas faine to doe for his ſonns. Her joy vvas a <hi>Vocall audible</hi> Joy: ſo let ours be, let our Tongues chaunt forth prayſes, and thanksgivings, let our diſcourſes beate vpon this theame: ſo it be prudently, and diſcreetely. Her Joy vvas a <hi>Manuall, handy Joy</hi> (ſo to ſpeake) a Joy that shooted forth into good vvorkes. Here vvas ſending of gifts probably, and giving to the poore: ſo let our <hi>hands</hi> be dilated vvith our <hi>hearts:</hi> let the needy and ſtranger have matter of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vvith vs, that ſo there may be a full Queere of Prayſers. Here vvas penning of Pſalmes &amp; hymnes for Poſterity to take notice of: ſo let vs doe ſomething to our povver, that after Ages may vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe our thankfullnes. And <hi>good Luck may He have vvith his Honour,</hi> vvho hath ſolemnized a day to be ſpoken of by future Times.</p>
            <p>But before vve proceede further in our Hallelujah it vvill not be amiſſe, to interpoſe an Hoſanna &amp; Prayer: juſt the Churches Method here. That God vvould ſtill and ſtill continue to doe greate things for vs, to be our Lord and faviour allvvays! That as there is novv an happy Amneſtia of old matters, ſo there may be a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20498:12"/>vvholeſome evacuation of all ſuch peccant humors &amp; principles vvhich may breede ſuch like <hi>Epidemicall diſeaſes</hi> in a State. For this purpoſe, I had thought to have made a <hi>Digreſsion,</hi> (if yet it be a digreſſion) and to commend to mens ſerious conſiderations ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Texts of Scripture. In this haſt I vvill only name one, that in S. Math. cap. 22. v. 21. Render vnto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and vnto God the things that are Gods. They are Chriſts ovvne vvords you knovv.</p>
            <p>Novv, till <hi>Heaven &amp; Earth shall paſſe avvay one title or Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta of his vvord shall in noe vviſe paſſe.</hi> And truely, if one Jota, or title of <hi>this vvord should paſſe;</hi> Heaven or Earth or both vvould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, paſſe avvay.</p>
            <p>Let but one of theſe Quaes paſſe: you shall ſee vvhat vvill follovv vpon it. If <hi>Caeſars quae</hi> paſſeth, the Kings Tribute &amp; Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's: novv <hi>Earth paſſeth avvay</hi> immediately. If <hi>Gods quae.</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke avvay Gods dues, (His vvorship &amp; the mantainance thereof) and the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven is paſsing avvay</hi> preſently. All Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion &amp; Devotion cleane vanisheth.</p>
            <p>Nay, doe but miſplace theſe Quae's once; and noe leſſe Confuſion vvill enſue. Put <hi>Gods Quae</hi> to <hi>Caeſar. Render vnto Caeſar</hi> &amp; the State <hi>the things that are Gods</hi> &amp; His Churches (<hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> his Religion) and vvhat comes of it? Nothing but plaine Atheiſme. All Religion ceaſeth. Neither Preiſts lips nor poeples eares in a very short time. Here <hi>Heaven paſſeth avvay againe.</hi> Againe put <hi>Caeſars Quae</hi> to <hi>Deus. Render vnto God</hi> &amp; the Church <hi>the things that are Caeſars</hi> (the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Religion as they make it) and then ere long noe Caeſar at all, nor ſecular Magiſtrate but merely Titular <hi>Domini ſine Terrâ Here Earth paſſeth avvay againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet againe, if vve admit onely one of the propoſitions and shut out the other: the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger is ſtill the ſame The <hi>Herodians</hi> vvere all for the firſt. <hi>Render vnto Caeſar</hi> &amp;c. and ſtayed there. Nothing but Earth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſed avvay</hi> from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The <hi>Romaniſts</hi> vvould ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs beleive. they are all for God &amp; his Church <hi>Re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der vnto God</hi> vvith
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20498:13"/>this noyſe &amp; hubhub they fill the aire. And ſo they order it that to <hi>them Earth paſſeth avvay.</hi> I ſayd vvell <hi>to them, to themſelves</hi> indee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and <hi>from</hi> all others. They ſvvallovv vp the Earth here vnder the praetext of Heaven. It is vvell if they let not Heaven paſſe in the meane time. Thus you ſee vvhat Danger there may be in leaving out this title (And) in the Text.</p>
            <p>Once more, if any dare to be ſo Atheiſtically Rebellious as to goe about to cancell that one vvord <hi>Reddite Render;</hi> ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly <hi>Heaven &amp; Earth</hi> both vvill <hi>paſſe avvay from them.</hi> Nor God nor King vvill be acknovvledged, nor Religion nor Policy, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, nor Heaven nor Earth poſſeſſed by ſuch. And vve holde but a third place. Let them take leede leaſt that fall to their lotts. The Summe of all is. God &amp; Caeſar, Religion &amp; the State cannot be ſeperated in the Text in the vvorld.</p>
            <p>But I vvell remember vvhere Jam. In the Magazene of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; Loyalty. For ſo (me thinkes) this goodly Audience ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be nothing els but a glorious Conſtellation of true hearted Chriſtians and Loyall Subjects.</p>
            <p>I Knovv vvell You make it your Religion, to make your frequent <hi>prayers &amp; Supplications for kings &amp; All that are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorithy over vs;</hi> to render them all honour &amp; love, all Homage &amp; Loyalty, in your hearts, by your tongues, vvith your good, vvith your Lives.</p>
            <p>I am ſure it is your faith. That the <hi>Sinne of Rebellion is as the Sinne of vvith-crafft 1. Sam. 15. 23.</hi> An interpretative renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of God Himſelfe: <hi>That Stubborneſſe is as Idolatry</hi> marke it as <hi>Idolatry,</hi> they are Samuels ovvne vvords, in the ſame place. I forbeare to make any gloſſe on that novv: That Mutterings &amp; vvhiſperings are the language of vvizards, and Dialect of Hell, as, odious to your Thoughts &amp; Eares, as in others Mouths. &amp; Penns. That Kings &amp; Princes are in their Goverments <hi>Solo Deo minores,</hi> as Tertull, profeſſed to Scapula: and therefore muſt not be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, much leſſe, oppoſed by Subjects, But in caſe entreatys &amp;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20498:13"/>Supplications may not prevaile, to leave Them <hi>to ſtand or full to their ovvne Master,</hi> as vvas the conſtant practiſe of the Primitive Churches. That, though they may be of the ſame mettall vvith our ſelves (although vve muſt yeeld them farre more refined and of a farre larger Size) yet vvhen they have Gods <hi>Stampe &amp; Image</hi> vpon them, they muſt paſſe <hi>Currant,</hi> prove as they vvill novv. Let Saul be one of the Lovveſt familys of the leaſt Tribe of Iſrael yet vvhen He is once elected King, He is novv <hi>conſecrated</hi> to God by that <hi>Sacred Oyle</hi> and becomes <hi>the Lords anoynted</hi> and not to be <hi>touched</hi> (though novv a very Tyrant) noe not by David, though by Divine right, his next, Succeſſor. That is is the <hi>Lord by vvhom all Kings reighne</hi> prov. 8.15. And the day of their <hi>Coronation</hi> on Earth, is the day of their <hi>Filiation</hi> in Heaven. Novv God calls them his ſonns (And vvho shall teach God hovv and vvhen to correct his ſonns?) <hi>Thou art my ſonne this day: have I begotten Thee.</hi> Begotten thee, <hi>Generatione</hi> ſc. <hi>Politica,</hi> that is, this day I have made thee King. This to be the primary, proper ſenſe of that place,<note place="margin">Cl. M.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Med<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in MS.</note> as alſo of Pſalme 110. a greate &amp; modeſt Critick dares avouch it out of the purport of the Texts. And hovv ſoever they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the myſtery, yet of <hi>Chriſt as Chriſt, Unctus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> the <hi>Lords anoynted.</hi> That God to ſet Princes above the reach of Subjects hands hath advanced them to the Dignity of a Deity. <hi>I have ſayd you are Gods.</hi> It is God that ſayth it, or if the Pſaimiſt yet it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the perſon of God as <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hirn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> gloſſeth. Kings <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as he goeth on to catechize his, it is in preſat: ad Catech.) Kings <hi>being but mort all men</hi> doe yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> beare the name of the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall God. This is your Religion.</p>
            <p>I Fully perſuade my ſelfe <hi>you</hi> make it a matter of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, That, to vvhom you ovve, for your <hi>Juſtitia Gladij</hi> the <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the ſvvord</hi> againſt <hi>forraine Invaſions:</hi> that to him you ought to pay tovvards vvarlick proviſion &amp; ſupplies: That, to vvhom you are endebted for your <hi>Gladius Justitiae,</hi> the <hi>Svvord of Juſtice</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20498:14"/>againſt Domeſtick Injurijs; that to Him you are to pay duty's for the vpholding of thoſe Courts of Juſtice: That, by vvhom, you enioy your <hi>Mare liberum,</hi> your Harveſt of the vvater, your ſafe merchandize, vnder vvhom you poſſeſſe your <hi>Terra Liberalis</hi> your rich Crops &amp; Lands; that to Him you are to pay Cuſtomes &amp; Taxes. This is your Allegance this is your Divinity. Yea and you can bring Scripture for all theſe, for Taxes 2, kings, 23. 35. for Cuſtomes Rom. 13. 7. for Fines &amp; Confiſcations Ezra 7. 26. &amp; cap. 10. 8. for all in one, in that forenamed Text: <hi>Render vnto</hi> Caeſar &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I verily beleeve, <hi>you</hi> thoroughly perceive, that <hi>Corrumpitur omne Imperantis officium &amp; diſſolvitur, ſi quis ad td, quod juſſus eſt, non obſequio debito, ſed conſilio non deſiderato, reſpondeat.</hi> It vvas a Captaines Speech in <hi>Gellius</hi> to a Pragmaticall Shipvvrigt, that vvould needes be ſcanning &amp; interpreting his Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and rather lend his counſell vncalled for then performe his office, Why, ſayth the, Captaine: <hi>Corrumpitur omne officium</hi> etc. If this may be allovved a Commander vvill be put quite out of office. Fare vvell all Authority. Neither vvill a Generall, or officer have any Command over his Regiments, nor a Maſter be able to beare vp himſelfe againſt his ſervant, or Apprentiſe, nor a Father command his child. You ſee all this and can eaſily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that many of thoſe Anticks you ſee in greate Buildings, vvhich make ſuch fearefull faces &amp; vſe ſuch hideous Poſtures as if the vvhole vveight of the building lay on their shoulders only, that if theſe be taken avvay the ſtructure vvill ſtand never the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: and ſo you beleeve, that State or Church is never the nearer to falling, out of vvhich ſome (vvho having leaſt reaſon, are moſt clamorous &amp; vnruly) be fairely casheired. Theſe are your <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimicks</hi> Theſe are vour <hi>Politicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I dare ſay for <hi>you,</hi> that, that <hi>Diſcipline</hi> &amp; <hi>order</hi> in the Church, vvhich fetcheth its Pedegree from <hi>Apoſtolicall Inſtitution,</hi> and hath held on in a Line of vninterrupted Succeſſion for 15000. Yeares togeather (as hath bin againe &amp; againe demonſtrated by your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20498:14"/>
               <hi>Hookers, Dovvnams, Carletons, Feilds</hi> and I knovv not hovv ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned, Pious, &amp; Modeſt vvriters of your ovvne Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.) that this Church Policy you vvillingly ſubmit vnto: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the vviſe mans Counſell <hi>Meddle not vvith them that are given to change.</hi> Prov. 24.21.</p>
            <p>I make noe Queſtion but <hi>you</hi> are fully convinced, that vvhat Authority <hi>Churchmen</hi> have more then <hi>Directive</hi> &amp; <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> vvhich extend's to <hi>externall Coaction</hi> that this is merely deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the <hi>King</hi> (vvho rightly poſſeſſeth vvhat the Pope uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped) and that therefore theſe Eccleſiaſticall Perſons fitt the <hi>Kings Commiſsioners</hi> in Eccleſiaſticall Courts, vvhere in their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are according to Lavves Eccleſiaſticall ratified by the King &amp; the vvhole State: And for this you can receive full ſatisfaction from S. Thom. Radley a Lavveyer, &amp; from the Acts and Statutes of our Kingdome.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but <hi>you</hi> ſee greate reaſon that vvhen men in Place shall <hi>ſecundum allegata &amp; probata</hi> be convicted peccant, that the Places therefore &amp; the Orders are not preſently to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molished. For if this may holde: then, dovvne vvith all Judges becauſe ſome have bin proved Corrupt, then, dovvne vvith all Nobles becauſe ſome have bin knovven Rebells: then, dovvne vvith all Kings becauſe ſome have bin Tyrants: then, turne all Common into a vvilde Anarchy, vvherein men vvill temper as vvell as the Jron &amp; Clay in the toes of his Image and ſo in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, dovvne vvith all the vvorld, Theſe are your <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I aſſure my ſelfe, that vvhere others take Liberty to <hi>prate</hi> againeſt <hi>you</hi> count it your duty to <hi>pray</hi> for all Superiours, and to <hi>prayſe</hi> God for this happy ſetled Government, vnder vvhich our State and Church hath flourished ſo many Decads of yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather. For to vvhat State hath Forraine Nations ſo vailed, as to ours? or by vvhat Hierarchy hath the Romane chaire ever bin(and is dayly) ſo shaken, as by ours? So that if to be <hi>Anti-Romane</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20498:15"/>be <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> men may ſpeake their pleaſures. And to vvhom doth both Church &amp; State (vnder God) ovve for this happines but to our <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> our moſt Gracious king CHARLES?</p>
            <p>I could vvish heartily, that Flattery vvere counted Treaſon. It is ſo in effect. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is Greeke for a Flatteror, a <hi>Complementall murderer.</hi> I vvould he had the punishment of ſuch a Malefactor. But our Saviour gives vs in charge to pay <hi>Caeſar bis dues.</hi> Nay made Himſelfe a Preſident. <hi>Conditor Caeſaris non cunctatus est Reddere Cenſum Caeſari.</hi> It is St. Bernards gloſſe vpon that place. <hi>The God of Caeſar ſtuck not to pay Tribute to Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> to Heathenish <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to Tyrant <hi>Tiberius Caeſar:</hi> and may not vve to ours? The Splendor of vvhoſe true <hi>Religion,</hi> The brightnes of vvhoſe <hi>vviſdome,</hi> The propitiouſnes of vvhoſe <hi>Clemency,</hi> The Candor of vvhoſe <hi>Juſtice, Temperance, Chaſtity</hi> have every vvhere rendered Him ſo truely glorious, that He ſeemes to be ſett farre above the reach, either of a <hi>Courtiers flattery</hi> or of an <hi>Orators Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole.</hi> This vve all knovve, and are not men, vnles vve all <hi>acknovvledge it in all places, vvith all thankfullnes.</hi> And novv (me thinkes) I heare all the Poeple, happily changing that Jevvish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, into a Chriſtian Religion: <hi>He is novv noe freind to Chriſt, that is not a freind to Caeſar, to ſuch a Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time I beleeve your Affections are all on fire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to your Hallelujah, and <hi>Eccho Back</hi> to <hi>Sion</hi> vvhat she did to the <hi>Heathen, The Lord hath done greate things for vs,</hi> vvho hath given vs ſo happy a <hi>Prince</hi> by vvhoſe <hi>vviſdome &amp; ſvveetenes</hi> ſuch a greate Deliverance hath bin nevvly vvrought for all Brittaine.</p>
            <p>Goe to, if you vvill, and let the <hi>ſcale</hi> of your Divine muſick reach as high and as deepe as ever any did or can.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Counſellers of State</hi> prayſe God and ſay. <hi>The Lord hath done greate things for vs.</hi> Our Cares may novv be employed in more Publick &amp; Catholick Deſighnes, vvhich have bin of late taken vp in the compoſing of theſe private Tumults.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20498:15"/>
            <p> Let the <hi>Clergy</hi> prayſe God &amp; ſay. <hi>The Lord hath done &amp;c. for vs.</hi> Novv there is hope that the Preiſts vvho beare the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vvill turne their faces all one vvay, in a decent vniformity.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Gentry</hi> prayſe God &amp; ſay. The <hi>Lord hath</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for us</hi> We are novv ſecured, that <hi>our Lands may be called after our ovvne names.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Univerſitys</hi> prayſe the Lord &amp; ſay. <hi>The Lord</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for vs.</hi> Novv may vve enioy the <hi>Polutecnia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Calotecnia,</hi> the Number &amp; beauty of our ſonns, vvithout any feares of proving Abortive by the Affrightments of vvarlick Alarums.</p>
            <p>Let the Merchants prayſe the Lord &amp; ſay <hi>The Lord</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for vs.</hi> Novv Traffick vvill be open, Novv our Burſes &amp; vvare hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes shall be thronged.</p>
            <p>To conclude, let all Perſons <hi>high</hi> &amp; <hi>lovve, youngmen</hi> &amp; <hi>maydens, old men &amp; children:</hi> Yea let vs call in our Fellovv Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Elements, the Meteors, the Fovvles, the Cattell, let all that have any <hi>breath,</hi> that have any <hi>being</hi> in our Island, prayſe the Lord, and make a Joyfull noyſe vnto our God, vvho <hi>hath done ſo greate</hi> ſo very <hi>greate</hi> (Lord hovv <hi>greate!</hi>) <hi>things for vs vvhereof <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve novv reioyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo Greate &amp; Good God vve prayſe Thee, vve magnifie Thee &amp;c-</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20498:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20498:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Good Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I knovv you vvould be ſatisfied in theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds vvhy vvas this thus raggedly Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? vvhy Printed? vvhy ſo ill Printed?</p>
            <p>To the firſt, I confeſſe it is too poore, yet pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to conſider. 1. That I am farre from my ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; have but a Portable. (I had allmoſt ſayd) a Pocket Library. 2. Of thoſe fevv da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes I had for <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, all but the tvvo laſt (verbo Sacerdotis) vvere runne out in Meditations another vvay. But ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations turned me out o<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it. Among the reſt theſe. 1. That my meſſage vvas to a full Audience, not to tvvo or three only. 2. To my Countrymen, and concerning our ovvne Country, and therefore it vvas fit I sho<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d be vvell vnderſtood of All.</p>
            <p>To t<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>econd. I vvas commanded by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to print, as neare as I could, vvhat I <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vvhich I have but obeyed</p>
            <p>To the laſt. Knovv, the Printer to be a meere ſtranger to language. And notvvithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my diligence in over looking him, did erre ſometimes and vpon a miſtake, print the full nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the coppyes of one sheete, ere it vvas corrected. VVhich errours I muſt be beholding to your penne to Correct vide eſpecially pag. 13. l. 9. &amp; 10.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
